[ Mid-tempo music plays ]
♪♪
-Cal!
-What kept you?
-Had to sneak past the old man.
Happy birthday.
♪♪
-[ Chuckles ]
-I want to swim.
-What?
-Come on, Ruthie.
-You're off your head, Innes!
♪♪
-Cal!
[ Giggles ]
♪♪
-[ Giggles ]
-Come on, Ruthie!
Whoo! Whoo!
-[ Chuckles ]
♪♪
-Flight's at midday,
so I should be back in London
this evening, sir.
-I thought you were
taking the week.
-Aye, well, change of plan.
-What happened?
-Me, basically.
[ Mobile vibrates ]
[ Sighs ] Hold on.
Hello?
-[ Sobbing ] Ruth?
-James, are you all right?
-[ Sobs ] It's Cal.
-What do you mean it's Cal?
-[ Sobbing ]
-James, what is going on?
[ Knock on door ]
♪♪
[ Police radio chatter ]
[ Breathing heavily ]
-DI Calder. No,
you don't want to see him.
♪♪
-[ Gasps ]
-There was nothing
they could do.
♪♪
-[ Shudders ]
-Why did you let her
near the body?
-Well, I tried to stop her.
-How is she now?
-[ Sighs ] She's in shock.
-Do they know
what happened?
-Traffic team are only
getting started,
but it looks like
he just went off the road.
-How?
-We don't know,
but Cora thinks she smelled
alcohol on the body.
-[ Sighs ] Okay.
Let Traffic do their work.
Tell 'em to call me as soon as
they have something to report.
And get Ruth
away from there.
Everything we've learned
about Ellen suggests
she was struggling emotionally
before she left for London.
We're trying
to work out why.
-Well, as I said, Ellen's
lifestyle was pretty intense.
Drink, drugs...
-No, I -- I get that.
But I'm starting to think
that the partying
may have been more
of a symptom than the cause.
I wonder if the cause...
may have been
Akmal's death.
-What makes you think that?
-Well, we have
a witness who says
that Ellen's problems began
just after Akmal died.
-Well, the timing
could just be a coincidence.
Perhaps Ellen was going through
something else at that time.
-Mm-hmm. Could be.
Did Ellen ever meet Akmal
when she was working here?
-I suppose she must have,
but then, she only did
a couple of shifts.
And when she was here,
she barely gave Akmal
a second look.
-So, there was no...
connection?
-None that I saw.
-But that doesn't mean
she wasn't affected by it.
Lots of people were.
The kindness
of the people here,
it's what's
helped us through.
-But when she was
in Langbank,
Ellen never mentioned
Akmal to you?
-Never.
-Okay. [ Chuckles ]
Well, it was just a theory.
I really am sorry for
bringing it all back up again.
-It's fine.
-I'll see myself out.
[ Door opens, closes ]
♪♪
-[ Breathes deeply ]
-I am sorry.
I really am.
Cal was a good guy.
[ Mobile chimes ]
Bit of a rogue maybe, but...
he had a good heart.
I mean, I'm not saying
me and him got on --
-Shh. Shut up a minute.
-Hey, it's me.
Just been up
to see Bobby Bain.
Definitely something
going on there.
Call me back.
-[ Gasps softly ]
We need to go to the Bains.
-Morning.
-Where's your mum and dad?
-Still sleeping.
-[ Snaps fingers ] Hey.
You hungry?
Head up to the big house.
Your gran'll make
some breakfast.
-[ Groans ]
Jesus.
I forgot how comfortable
this bed was.
What time is it?
You okay?
-I was thinking about
the day she was born.
[ Chuckles ]
14 hours in labour.
I thought she was
never coming out.
-Sure Ellen was always
hard work.
-She was.
Were you shocked?
-What?
-Ellen...
When they told you
she was dead, were you shocked?
-Jesus Christ.
What kind
of a question is that?
-Because I wasn't.
I mean...
I felt numb and...
you know, grief, anger.
I mean, I f--
I felt all the things
I was supposed to feel, but...
[ Chuckles ]
I wasn't surprised.
You know, I thought, "Well, aye.
Aye, that makes sense."
-Ellen didn't
deserve to die.
-No, I didn't --
I didn't say
she deserved it.
[ Sighs ] She was so...
She was so reckless.
[ Vehicle approaching ]
Someone's here.
[ Door opens ]
[ Sheep bleating ]
♪♪
-Can I help you?
-Well, you can start
by telling us
why Cal Innes
was with you last night.
-Well, he popped by
for a few drinks.
-Cal Innes... popped by...
to see you?
-That's right.
-Didn't realise
you were pals.
-[ Scoffs ] Did you not?
-Well, as far
as I remember it,
you two couldn't stand
each other back in the day.
-What's the issue here?
-Cal's van went off
the road last night.
Just outside of Aith.
-God. Is he all right?
-He's dead.
-Jesus.
I mean, that's awful.
I'm sorry.
How long was he here
for last night?
-Arrived about seven.
Must've left... just before 11.
-So, that's four hours
drinking, then?
-And talking.
-About what?
-Mostly he talked
about you.
-How much did Cal
have to drink?
-Not sure I should answer that.
-Yes, you fucking should!
[ Breathes deeply ]
-I'd say he had a fair few
before he left.
-And you just
let him drive?
-I told him not to,
I told him to stay the night,
but he was having
none of it.
-What did you do
after he left?
-Crashed out
in the workshop.
-Anybody vouch for you?
-No.
-Why does he need
someone to vouch for him
if it was an accident?
♪♪
What was he doing here?
-We need to go
to the station.
-I'm not sure
that's a good idea.
[ Sighs ] Maybe
we could call in.
[ Car lock beeps ]
-If you can do an extra
couple of hours on Friday,
that would be great.
-Yep. No problem.
I heard about Cal.
You okay?
-I'm fine.
It's Ruth I'm worried about.
Sandy said she turned up
at the accident site.
Saw the body.
-Do we know how it happened?
-Cora thinks
Cal had been drinking.
-[ Sighs ] Is there anyone
with Ruth?
-I asked Sandy
to look after her.
-Sandy?
-There was no-one else.
-Better than nothing,
I suppose.
Aye, and there's that.
-Where are they now?
-Rosemary was bailed
this morning.
She's staying at her mum's.
Ayre's on his way
to Peterhead.
They'll hold him there
until his trial.
-Tosh, can I speak to you?
-Sure. Get Uniform to do
a welfare check on Rosemary,
just in case there's
any backlash from this.
-Will do.
-All we know right now
is Cal's van went off the road
sometime last night.
Doesn't look like
any other vehicles were --
-Did you speak
with the Sadats?
-This morning. Why?
-What happened?
-Nothing.
I was following up on a theory
about Ellen and Akmal.
Why? What's the problem?
-[ Breathes deeply ]
Their solicitor
just called.
It seems Azir
and Farida felt
that you were aggressive
in your questioning
and caused them
undue distress.
-Okay, that is not
what happened.
-Well, the solicitor's
threatening a formal complaint.
And she says she wants
all future contact
to be made through her.
You need to back off a bit.
-Hang on.
They must've made that call
the minute I left.
-Suggests they were upset.
-I need to see the report
on the Akmal Sadat accident.
-Why?
-If the Sadats
are calling in lawyers,
they're hiding something.
-What did I just say
about backing off?
-I want to see
the report, Harry.
-[ Sighs ]
♪♪
-Caroline's fixed it.
We won't be getting
any more surprise visits.
-We can't hold them off forever.
-We won't have to.
This will all blow over
in a couple of weeks.
-It's not going
to blow over, Azir.
-We just carry on
as normal.
-Normal? There's nothing normal
about any of this.
It's insane.
And I'm not taking those!
You can't keep
numbing me to this.
-I'm just trying
to keep you calm.
-I don't want to be calm!
I'm not like you!
You -- you go around acting
like nothing's happened.
Like a robot!
-What else can I do?!
Huh?
How else am I supposed to get us
out of the mess you put us in?!
If you knew the things
I've had to do to protect you.
The things
I've done for you.
♪♪
I have a meeting.
I need you to stay here
and do nothing. Okay?
♪♪
[ Door opens ]
-They lost a kid, Tosh.
If it were me,
the last thing I'd want
is for it all to be
dragged up again.
-But to call in
their lawyer?
-Okay, granted,
it's a bit extreme,
but then, you know,
maybe they felt you were...
-What? Doing my job?
-Look, I'm just saying.
There's a lot of folk
who feel for Farida and Azir.
-Your little harem?
-No, not just the nursery mums.
Half the Isles turned out
for the memorial.
-Look, I cannot
just drop this
because people
feel sorry for them.
-Yeah, I know, but...
maybe go gently, eh?
[ Door opens, closes ]
Like, we have to live here.
-I'll talk to you later.
Ruth, I'm so sorry
about Cal.
-You need to bring in
Bobby Bain.
-Okay, why?
-Because he was
with Cal last night.
-They were drinking
at the farm.
-Not just drinking.
Listen...
-Hey, it's me.
Just been up to see Bobby Bain.
Definitely something
going on there.
Call me back.
-When did Cal leave this?
-Last night,
after he left the farm.
-Did you call him back?
-I didn't pick it up
until this morning.
Point is, Cal found out
something about Bobby,
and Bobby was shifty
when we spoke to him.
-When?
-What?
-When did you speak
to Bobby?
-This morning.
-[ Exhales deeply ]
Could I have a word?
-Ruth, I'm sorry about...
-We're wasting time here.
The sooner we move on Bobby...
-How are you feeling?
-How am I feeling?
-About Cal.
-Well, I'll feel
a whole lot better
when you bring in
Bobby Bain.
-For what?
-For what?!
Did you not hear
the message?
Cal finds out
something about him,
next thing, he's driving
his van off the road?
-Have you spoken to James?
-No, I --
I haven't had time.
-Well, don't you think
maybe you should?
He probably needs
a friend right now.
-I'd rather just focus
on Bobby.
So, are we bringing him in,
or -- or what?
-I think we should wait
for Cora and the Crash
Investigation team.
-Oh, for Christ's sake.
-Ruth, listen to me.
You need to stay
out of this.
-Okay.
Know what? Forget it.
-Ruth?
-Lab results on those new pills
show they're pretty high grade.
-And?
-Well, it is unusual
for up here. I mean...
[ Door slams ]
-Sandy, take her
to James Innes.
Stay with her
and keep her out of trouble.
-Sure.
She going to be okay?
-I don't know.
[ Dog barking ]
-Hi. I've got to go.
There's toast and eggs
in the kitchen for you.
-I'm not hungry.
-Hey...
-[ Sniffles ]
-What's the matter?
-Just thinking about Ellen.
-[ Sighs ]
I know, I know.
It's awful.
Is there anything I can do?
-Can you transfer me
some money?
-[ Scoffs ] I gave you
30 quid yesterday.
-It's fine, it's fine.
Doesn't matter.
-[ Sighs ]
[ Mobile chimes ]
I'll ping 50 over, okay?
-Thanks.
-But I need to go.
I'll see you later.
-See you.
[ Door opens, closes ]
[ Mobile vibrating ]
-Hello?
-Cal's dead.
-What?
-Last night. Crashed his van
on the way back from the farm.
Police came to see me
about it this morning.
-Why?
-'Cos he was with me last night.
-What do you mean
he was with you?
-Never mind.
There's a good chance
they'll want to speak to you.
If they do,
you don't mention me
and you don't mention
the money.
-Well -- well, what do I say?
-I don't care.
Just as long as you
keep my name out of it.
-Bob, Bob!
♪♪
-You don't have to go in
if you don't want to.
I mean, we can just go
somewhere else.
You know, when my da died,
I didn't want to talk to anyone.
Just wanted to hide away
from the world.
But the thing about grief is,
it needs to be shared.
You can't do it
on your own.
-Jesus! Fine, I'm going.
Anything to shut you up.
-[ Sighs ]
-[ Breathes deeply ]
♪♪
[ Police radio chatter ]
[ Quiet, indistinct chatter ]
♪♪
-Ruth.
How did this happen, eh?
What are we going to do?
♪♪
-[ Sobbing ] Come here.
-[ Breathing shakily ]
♪♪
-Billy?
-Aye?
-Get me Heather Bain's number.
-I don't get it.
It's Azir
and Farida's kitchen.
So what?
-On the worktop.
By the fridge.
The cleaning caddy.
Isn't that one of yours?
-Looks like it.
Guess I must've
left it there.
-But this photograph was taken
on the day of Akmal's accident.
Were you at the Sadats'
house that day?
-No!
But I probably left the caddy
there a few days before.
-Is there any chance
that Ellen was at the Sadats'
house that day?
-Don't see why
she would've been.
-Well, maybe they got her in
for a shift without you knowing.
-[ Scoffs ] I doubt it.
They're not the type.
Plus Ellen was a pretty
useless cleaner.
Why are you asking, anyway?
-I think Akmal's death
had an impact on Ellen.
I think it's the reason
why she was struggling.
Did she ever talk about it?
-Well, aye. For a while, it was
all anyone was talking about.
-Yeah, but beyond that.
Did you ever get the sense
that it was on her mind?
-Ellen wasn't one
for dwelling on sad stuff.
Not when there was a party
or a boy to think about.
-I don't know.
I think Ellen was a lot deeper
than people seem to think.
-Oh! Sorry, I need to go.
I'll tell you what --
I'll check if I'm missing
a caddy when I get home.
-Thanks.
I appreciate that.
[ Door opens, closes ]
[ Mobile dialling ]
-McCabe.
-Hi, Billy, it's me.
Going to need you to pull
some call records for me.
♪♪
[ Birds calling ]
-You okay?
-I can't do
other people's grief.
-[ Exhales deeply ]
-How is he?
-James? James is...
well, he's wrecked,
but he's got good people
around him.
Unlike you.
-I'm fine.
-Amma's gone
to stay with a pal.
Decided to take
some time out.
-I see.
-Just need some space,
you know?
Look, I'm sorry
about the other night.
I was out of order.
-It's okay.
-No, it's not.
It's not. I shouldn't
have reacted like that.
I shouldn't have got angry.
-You and Dad were close.
I get it.
-That's not
why I got angry.
I think you might
be right.
-About what?
-About Dad
and Stella Quinn.
♪♪
-[ Strumming guitar strings ]
-And those dates
are confirmed?
-It looks like it.
-What's going on?
-I pulled the call records
for the Sadats
and Heather and Ellen
from around the time
Akmal Sadat died.
-Why?
-Well, because I think there's
something about Akmal's death
they're not telling us,
and I think Heather and Ellen
were involved.
-I --
-Look, just -- just listen to me
just for a minute. Please.
The day after the accident,
Ellen called Heather
seven times.
Now, up until that day,
Heather was lucky to get a call
from Ellen once a week.
Azir's records show
that he and Heather
talked 16 times
in the days
after Akmal's death.
Some of those calls
lasted over an hour,
and Heather claims
neither she nor Ellen
was working at the Sadats' place
on the day of the accident,
but we have her
cleaning caddy at the scene.
What's it doing there?
-Akmal's death was investigated.
-I know.
-Police, pathologist,
child services,
and even my office decided it
was nothing more than a tragedy.
-Maybe you got it wrong.
-Why?
Because of some
unusual call patterns?
A child had died.
It wasn't a normal time
for anyone.
-And for Azir Sadat,
it was the worst time.
The man lost his son.
I can't imagine how I would feel
if that was my child,
but I am pretty sure
the last person I'd be calling
in the days after it
is my cleaner.
-I think you need to focus
on who killed Ellen Quinn.
-Harry, I am!
We know Ellen was struggling
before she went to London.
Now we know the date of Akmal's
death was important to her.
I think this could be it.
-She felt sorry for him.
-Or maybe it was guilt
she felt.
Maybe she knew
something about it.
Maybe she knew the truth,
and maybe that's
what got her killed.
-That's a lot
of maybes in there.
-[ Sighs ]
-When was this?
-Ages ago.
It was my first term at uni.
I was back home for a bit.
-And did you see anything?
-All I remember is
that Stella was around.
A lot. At the kirk,
sometimes at the house.
I didn't see anything, but
I spoke to Jean this morning,
and apparently, she walked in
on Dad and Stella one day
at the manse.
And that's, I think, what put
an end to their relationship.
-How long did it go on for?
-Couple of months.
Two at the most.
One day, Stella just
stopped coming.
-Why?
-No idea.
Next time I saw her, she was
at the church marrying Kieran.
-Did he ever say
anything about her?
-God, no.
He did keep his distance from
the Bains after that, though.
-Why?
-You have no business
being in there, and...
-What the hell?
-I'm not putting up with it!
This is outrageous!
Get out my house!
-I didn't mean to upset you.
-What's going on?
-He's trying to blacken
my brother's name!
Body's not even cold,
and this bastard's
accusing him of dealing!
-I didn't say
that Cal was dealing.
-Bullshit! He's just asked me
if I ever saw him with pills.
-What? Why would you ask that?
-Let's talk about it later.
-There's nothing
to talk about.
-Why would you ask
if Cal was dealing?
-I found these in his room.
New drugs started coming
onto the Isles a few months ago.
We've no idea
who's behind it,
but whoever it is,
they use bags like these.
-That's it?
That's all you've got?
-Well, he's got a point.
It's not much.
-The pills are sourced
in Aberdeen.
My Drug Squad contact
down there confirmed it.
And I have a witness who says
the pills come in every month --
regular, which means --
-Yes, all right. I get it.
Could you... could you
give us a minute?
Yeah.
[ Footsteps retreating ]
-I remember Sandy Wilson
when he was at school.
He was a wee shit then
and he's a wee shit now.
-James, how often was Cal
taking your stock to Aberdeen?
-Oh, I don't know.
Not that often.
-Once a month?
-You're taking
his side on this!
-I'm not taking
anyone's side.
Sandy might've jumped
the gun a bit.
I know that Cal
was up to something.
Let's face it.
It's not really
a surprise, is it?
-My brother was a good guy.
-Yeah, he tried to be.
Look, none of this
is important right now.
I'll talk to Sandy.
-It's Neil Bain
you want to talk to.
-Why do I need
to talk to Neil Bain?
-He was always
hanging around here.
I told Cal to stay clear.
If there's dealing,
he'll be behind it.
[ Scoffs ]
Him and the other one
were here the other day.
Couple of fly men.
-What other one?
-Think I'm bloody stupid.
-James, what other one?
-Bobby Bain.
-Alan, will you stay
with James?
We need to find Neil Bain.
-Wait, we're looking
for him because...?
-Because I want to know why
he and Bobby Bain
were up here with Cal.
Keys?
-Maybe we should
let Tosh know.
-Why? Er, do you need
to ask her permission?
-No. I just think I should call
her and keep her up to speed.
-Fine, go ahead.
Do that, then.
I'd hate for you
to get a row.
-That's not going to work.
I'm not 12.
-[ Sighs ]
-[ Sighs ] Christ.
I'll do the talking.
-Fine, but I'll do
the driving.
Keys?
[ Car lock beeps ]
[ Sheep bleating ]
♪♪
-Hey, you all right?
-Have you seen this?
-Don't worry about it.
-Don't worry about it?
It says that Ellen
and the Strachan girl
were in a cult
with this... freak.
-Ellen wasn't
into that stuff.
-How would you know?
-She was a lot of things,
but she wasn't stupid.
-So, what about last night?
-What do you mean?
-What do I mean?
I mean, what the hell
happened with Cal Innes?
-I don't know.
-A man dies after spending
the night drinking with you,
and all you can say is,
"I don't know"?
-What else
do you want me to say?
-[ Scoffs ]
You don't seem
too concerned.
-Stella and Kieran
seem better.
-Better how?
-Well, they're talking
for a start.
-Aye, well, let's hope
he can talk some sense into her.
That girl needs reminding
who her family is.
-What's that supposed
to mean?
-It means she had no right
breaking bread with the Knoxes.
-"Breaking bread"?
[ Chuckling ]
Are you serious?
She went over
to talk to the boy.
-You're defending her?
-She just lost
her daughter!
-And that means
we have to hand over
everything
we've worked for?
-Everything I worked for!
Me!
Don't worry.
There's nothing left
for us to hand over.
♪♪
-Right, Lou, what are you
thinking about a wee bun
for the way home, eh?
Huh? That sound good?
[ Chuckles ]
Oh.
Farida.
♪♪
Are you all right?
-[ Sighs ]
[ Mobile rings ]
Hey.
[ Dog barking ]
-Remember,
I'll do the talking.
-Understood.
-You're just here to observe.
-Seen and not heard.
-That's the gist of it.
[ Knock on door ]
-DI Calder.
Mind if we come in?
We need to talk to you about
your relationship with Cal.
-Cal?
-Cal Innes.
You two were friends.
-Not really.
I knew him, that's all.
-"Knew him"?!
So, you heard he died?
-Yeah, he was in
an accident.
-Who told you
it was an accident?
-[ Scoffs ]
I don't -- I don't know.
I ju-- I just heard.
-When did you last
speak to Cal?
-Er, I don't know.
Ages ago.
We weren't that close.
I never really knew him.
-Really? Hmm.
'Cos his brother said that you
and him were dealing together.
-Dealing?
Dealing what?
-Pills. The ones that Cal was
bringing in from the Mainland
every month.
-I don't know
anything about that.
-Okay. Right.
Well, here's
what we'll do, then.
DC Wilson here's
going to call in a Search team.
We'll get them
to go over the place,
and while
they're doing that,
we'll get the IT team
from Inverness,
they'll start going
through your calls, texts,
chats, internet history...
-What? I haven't
done anything.
-Well, you have nothing
to worry about, then, have you?
But then, of course,
there's the witness.
-What witness?
-Oh, the -- the one
that DC Wilson found.
The one who identified you
as the person
that sold them the pills.
-[ Sighs ]
Look, I didn't sell them.
Maybe gave a few away,
but Cal was the one
that brought them up here.
-So, it was you and Cal?
-Mostly Cal.
-What about Bobby?
Look, we know that you and him
spoke with Cal yesterday.
We know that Cal was up
at the Bain farm last night,
so you need to start
by telling me
what Bobby Bain's part
in all of this is!
-Bobby didn't have
a part in this.
-Make the call.
-No, no. Wait, wait.
Right.
Okay. Fine.
♪♪
[ Sighs ]
Bobby only got onboard
a few days ago.
-Came onboard how?
-He said he had some money.
He wanted us to bring in
a bigger stash, but Cal refused.
He turned Bobby down.
-So, why were Cal and Bobby
together last night?
-I -- I don't know.
-How much money
are we talking?
-Looked like a lot.
-So you saw it?
-Yeah.
It was in a bag,
full of cash.
Thousands, I reckon.
♪♪
[ Door closes ]
[ Sighs ]
-[ Singing ]
* Where's your foot gone? *
* Where's your foot? *
Oh, here's Mummy.
Hey.
-Hi.
[ Sighs ]
Where is she?
-[ Sighs ]
[ Louise coos ]
-Says she wants
to speak to you.
But, Tosh, like,
go easy, would you?
-Yeah.
-Okay.
-How are you doing,
Farida?
Donnie says
you wanted to see me?
-He learned to ride
his bike here.
Me and Azir brought him.
It was orange,
the bike.
He loved it.
And he was so quick.
One lesson and he was racing
around us, laughing.
[ Breathes deeply ]
I can still smell him.
If I close my eyes
and focus,
I can smell the heat
on his hair.
[ Sobs ]
It was my fault.
-What was your fault,
Farida?
I fell asleep.
I was so tired.
And Azir had given me
these new tablets,
but I must've
taken too many
or maybe I forgot
and I'd taken some before.
I struggle with my moods.
Azir helps me
manage them.
I only woke up because
she was screaming, Ellen,
in the garden.
And Heather was leaning
over me.
Shaking me.
I couldn't get
my head to work.
And she was saying,
"It's Akmal."
And I said, "No.
He's in his room."
And she said...
"Oh, Farida."
And I saw why Ellen
was screaming.
[ Sobbing ] She was at
the bottom of the garden...
on her knees.
And he was lying
across her.
My beautiful boy...
had died...
alone in that loch...
and I'd slept through it.
-Farida...
I am so sorry
this happened.
I have to ask you
a few things, okay?
What happened after Heather
and Ellen found Akmal?
-Azir came home, and he was
crying and shouting at me.
Saying it was all my fault.
-What happened then?
-She took over.
Heather told Azir
to call the ambulance.
She told him to tell them that
he was there when it happened.
We would say, we took our eyes
off him for a few minutes,
and he must've got into
the garden and into the loch...
-Why? Why were you
to say that?
-Because she said
we'd lose it all.
The pills.
They weren't prescribed.
Azir was giving them to me.
He'd lose his job.
I'd be prosecuted, and they'd
take Zuma away from us.
So, we lied...
to everyone.
We betrayed our boy.
-Come here. Come here.
-[ Sobbing ]
-It's all right.
It's all right.
♪♪
-Farida?
Where are you?
I'm getting worried.
You -- you need the --
[ Vehicle approaching ]
♪♪
-It has to be
Ellen's money.
-We don't know that
for sure.
-Well, we know the Bains
are struggling.
The farm hasn't
made profit for years.
I mean, come on, where's
Bobby Bain going to find cash
to get into
the drug business?
-Look, even if it is
Ellen's money,
she lost it
before she was killed.
-Says Howell.
Maybe she lied to him.
Maybe she picked up the money
after she got away from them.
She runs into Bobby
and he kills her for it.
Maybe that is what Cal
found out last night.
And if Cal was onto Bobby,
that's reason enough
for him to want him dead.
-Well, first, we need to prove
that it is Ellen's money.
I mean, Bobby could've got it
from another source.
-Then we need to access
his bank records.
-Then you'll need
to talk to Tosh.
-Sandy!
-This has gone too far.
-He was there
because of me.
♪♪
Cal went to see Bobby because
I needed to know something.
Just something
I can't tell you about, but...
[ Sighs ]
He went there last night
because he was wanting
to help me.
And now, he's dead.
That... stupid, infuriating,
drug-dealing arsehole is dead,
and I'm pretty sure
that it's my fault.
♪♪
So, I really need
to do this.
Do you understand?
-I'll see what I can do.
Okay.
♪♪
-I want you to know
that I only did what I did
to keep my family.
-You lied about
your son's death.
-We were in shock,
and Heather was making
all the decisions.
We were frightened.
-What did Ellen
think about it?
-I think she wanted
to tell the truth,
but Heather
wouldn't let her.
Heather controlled it all.
As soon as we started lying,
she had us.
-Had you?
In what way?
-It started just
after the memorial.
Said she needed some money.
Made it sound like
it was a loan.
-She blackmailed you?
-Has been ever since.
-[ Sighs ]
Even so, that still
doesn't change the fact
that you and Farida lied.
-It was an accident.
A tragedy
we'll never get over.
How it happened?
Why it happened?
Just details.
-Akmal was your family.
He was your son.
And he deserved better
than a sordid cover-up.
Those details you talk about
were the record of his passing,
and they should have been
treated with the proper respect.
-[ Sighs ]
♪♪
-I don't understand
how we missed this.
They were interviewed. Social
Services investigated them.
-It was an awful thing,
and it happened to nice people.
Nobody wants
to think the worst.
-We'll need
to reopen the case.
-Farida Sadat's statement.
-Thanks.
Now, can you tell Grant to go
and secure the Sadat house?
Let us know if Forensics
find anything.
-Sure. Why are you
going over the house?
-I want their car
processed, too.
-But they've already
admitted to it.
-I know.
-If you're looking
for evidence of Akmal's death,
it was months --
-This isn't about Akmal.
It's about Ellen.
Azir just admitted
that Ellen wanted to tell
the truth about the accident,
and we know she tried
to call him on the day she died.
Ellen was a threat
to the Sadats.
You call me
if they find anything?
-Aye. Where will you be?
-With Heather Bain.
-Bobby's bank records
have just come through.
This guy's broke.
-Does it -- I mean, there's no
way Bobby Bain's managed
to raise thousands
off his own back.
-Ah, doesn't mean
he got it from Ellen.
-No, but the odds
are shortening.
-There you are.
[ Plates clink ]
-Even if he is struggling,
would he really kill
his own niece for money?
I mean, the Bains...
-These are London transactions.
-What?
-All of these
debit card payments.
Er, last transaction
was the 18th of April.
That is three days
before Ellen came back.
-Bobby was in London?
-I need to make
a phone call.
[ Vehicle approaches ]
[ Car door slams ]
-They lost a child!
A five-year-old son.
And what did you do?
You blackmailed them.
-[ Scoffs ] Don't know
what you're on about.
-No, don't give me that.
Farida told me everything.
-Oh, I wouldn't put too much
store in what Farida says.
She gets confused.
-Don't you dare!
You don't get to make
judgments on anyone,
not after what you did.
-What I did? [ Chuckles ]
Oh, aye, you're full
of sympathy for her now,
but would you lot
have been so understanding
if you'd turned up
that day?
A kid in the loch and a mother
blasted out of her mind.
She told you
what happened?
Farida doesn't remember
what happened.
-She remembers
you extorted them.
-I didn't extort anyone.
But do you know what?
Maybe I should have,
because without me,
they'd have lost everything.
I did a good thing.
-[ Scoffs ]
And what about Ellen?
-What about her?
-Where were you
when she needed you?
When she was struggling
with what happened.
What did you do then?
-I was always there for Ellen.
-You sent her to Langbank.
-Because she needed help.
-Because you needed
to shut her up.
You handed her over
to Azir Sadat
because you wanted him to find
a way to keep her from talking.
-Ellen was never
going to talk.
She didn't break down
because of Akmal.
Aye, she was upset.
We all were.
That's not why she left.
-Then why did she leave?
-Who knows?!
And who cares?
Ellen was a nightmare.
I was glad to see
the back of her.
♪♪
[ Mobile ringing ]
-Alex?
-Forensics have
found something.
[ Police radio chatter ]
-Here you go.
-So, I've just spoken
to my DC.
I'd asked him to check
with Ellen's flatmate
to see if she could confirm
that Bobby Bain was at Ellen's
on the 18th.
-And?
-And she couldn't.
-Well, then, that's that.
-Well, not quite.
My DC found an incident
report from that day.
A call-out to Ellen's flat.
Domestic disturbance.
A neighbour called it in.
-Were there any details?
-Oh, yes. She said that Ellen
was arguing with an older man,
but he'd gone by the time
the Uniforms showed up.
-Well, we don't know
it was Bobby.
-Yes, we do. The neighbour
snapped the guy on her phone
and my team
have ID'd Bobby.
♪♪
-Azir, I want to ask you about
the night Ellen Quinn died.
Did you have any contact
with her that night?
We found this blanket
in your car.
Can you confirm
it's yours, Azir?
The colour and the fabric
are similar
to fibres we found
in Ellen's hair.
You got any
thoughts on that?
-No.
-Well, we also found
blood traces in your car.
Our Forensic team believe
they're relatively fresh.
No more than, say,
a week old.
-I didn't kill her.
-But you were with her?
-Yes.
-On the night she died?
-When I didn't answer her call,
she came to the house.
-What time was that?
-It was late.
She was wet. Injured.
-Why did she come to you?
-She wanted money.
Said she was in trouble
and had to leave Shetland.
I told her I didn't have any.
She started getting angry.
Farida was asleep.
I -- I didn't want her upset.
-So, what did you do?
-I told her I'd try and get her
some in the morning.
And then she left.
-You told me Ellen wanted
to tell the truth about Akmal.
-We all did.
-But Heather stopped you?
-Yes.
-Still, if Ellen did choose
to come forward,
that would be a problem.
-I didn't kill Ellen.
-I don't believe you, Azir.
You see, if Ellen turned up
at your house and then left,
how come we have evidence
that she was in your car?
She threatened to tell the truth
about Akmal, didn't she?
She told you she was
going to come forward.
-No.
-And there she was,
on your doorstep,
threatening your family.
-I didn't kill her.
-Then how did she get
into your car?!
-Because I was worried
about her!
It was late.
She was on her own.
When she left,
I drove after her.
-You chased after her?
-To -- to make sure
she was okay.
I caught up with her.
Told her to get in.
-And did she?
-Yes.
-And then what happened?
-I asked her where
she wanted to go.
I told her
I'd take her anywhere.
-Where did she want to go?
Azir.
Where did you take Ellen?
♪♪
-Bobby Bain is lying.
-They're all lying.
Ellen came home that night.
♪♪