And we're sure this is our Jane Doe?
That's her. It was my case,
Lucy Cook's abduction.
She disappeared from her father's house.
No sign of forced entry,
no trail to follow.
So where's Abuelo?
He's on a spiritual walkabout.
-What's your name?
-Don't talk to her.
Tell me.
Where you coming in from, Shane?
It's funny you should turn up
looking for Abuelo
around the same time as me.
Yeah, well, who's to say?
The world's full of coincidences.
Did his father get in touch with you?
-His father?
-Yeah, he called today.
Were you close with Maggie Cook
back in the day?
Yeah, of course we were friendly.
Well, that girl who went off El Capitan
was her daughter.
Lucy?
Jesus! Fuck!
I found it up top.
You just may have stumbled
on something, Ranger Vasquez.
Can I help you?
Hold up! I just want to talk!
You shouldn't keep helping them, Lu.
They're bad people.
Who isn't?
You!
I rally all who are chosen
Who don't let society hold them
Asylum for the hurt and the broken
Precious metal, I am golden
Of the moon and the sun
Where I'm from is outside of the matrix
It has begun, revolution
We gotta say this
Call it what you want
Call it what you need
There's a shift
There's a glitch in this rеality
Now it's up to us
Now it's up to me
To invoke what was spoken
Through thе air that we breathe
I'm not sure I understand.
I mean, I get these three.
X marks the spot and all.
But how are you connecting
the guy from the river with them?
Where does Teddy Redwine fit?
Well, anyone looking
for weed inside the park
would usually find their way to Teddy.
He was into other shit as well,
but nothing too heavy.
I went and saw him to see
if he knew anything about the pills.
Put the squeeze on him
to find out what he could.
Next, he's getting pulled
out of the water.
It was a bad move by me
jamming him into it.
So Teddy, Lucy, the drugs.
You think this Abuelo guy
could be behind all of it?
Did you hear back from your friend
in Mariposa PD?
They seen any of those pills there?
Said they're starting to see more,
but no idea of the source.
-We heading back to that mine?
-I am.
What, I get a time-out
'cause of yesterday?
You tell me what happens
if I hadn't found a horse missing.
Gosh, Dad, I don't know. Nothing good.
I told you I screwed up.
I won't sneak the family car out again
without asking.
Someone told me
you should never go in those places alone!
There's some extra gear in the box.
Would help out in the parking lot?
I was hoping to slip out and have lunch
with my granddaughter today.
We could turn off the lights,
wait for them to go away.
That'll help.
If you're waiting for a ball game
to break out, I got two bad knees.
Oh. Oh, yeah, no. Uh…
I work at Foot Locker up in Tahoe.
Uh-huh.
Um, sorry. I came down because, uh…
I knew Lucy Cook when she was little.
I don't know what to do with that.
Sorry for your loss.
Oh, no, no, no. It's not like that.
I haven't seen her in…
I don't know. A long time.
Um…
Are you working on her case?
The disappearance?
No, that'd be Agent Turner,
but he's sort of moved on
to the next horrible phase of her life.
And he's not here.
Um, well, can I wait for him?
Sure. Yeah.
Yeah, he'd love to talk to you.
Nice guy. And it's his birthday today.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, thank you.
Nice and easy.
Don't want to go down there again.
Okay.
The ground should be stable here,
but if it gives a little
just step back, okay?
Okay.
This is what? An old gold mine?
Probably been here since, like, 1850s.
Thousands of these
abandoned around the state.
-I didn't know this one existed.
-Lucky for us, I found it, huh?
It would definitely make for
a good place to hide.
Yeah. Or to be doing
something you shouldn't.
These are all connected somehow.
It's like an underground tunnel system.
Watch out for rusty nails, hey.
Temperature's way up down here.
Air's not going to be great.
Probably traces of arsenic.
Arsenic?
The bad guys use ventilators
and we get nothing?
Hold on.
What is that?
What? Is it a cave-in?
Close your eyes.
Fuck! What?!
Ah!
Oh! You never said anything about bats!
Watch out for bats.
Using the mines to run product?
That would be the bet.
We're still inside the park here, right?
Yeah. Looks like a shortcut
through the mountain.
Found something.
Animals got to it.
Vultures. Picked it clean.
I don't think Abuelo's
coming back from his walkabout.
This is Turner. I got something for you.
Single turkey vulture
working on the maxilla bone there.
A couple ravens
showed up to crash the party.
What's your best guess
on how long this has been here?
Five or six days?
Looks longer than that.
Yeah, vultures accelerate decay.
It can throw off a timeline.
This, definitely inside a week.
Think you can find me
some more of the remains?
Oh. It might take a while.
Can't we just look
for birds circling around?
You must be new here. Is she new?
-LA.
-Ah.
It's a misconception
that vultures circle the dead.
They're too large
to flap their wings to fly,
so they find air thermals
to help them soar.
If you want a vulture to help find a body,
you need to look lower,
so tree branches, fence posts.
-This needs to be a ground search.
-You stay here with Morris.
You're leaving me with…
Let me know if you find something.
Vultures aren't equipped to hunt,
which makes them
the only animals in the world
that depend on death as a food source.
They hone in on the chemicals
that are released during decay.
They descend to the remains,
and they begin to feast.
They start with the eyes,
then the skin, tissues.
Always leave the spine.
They really are amazing creatures.
Wish I loved anything
as much as you love these birds.
Now what vultures love more than anything…
brains.
That's brains?
Crystalline.
Roughly a week old, I'd say.
What do you think, Ranger Vasquez?
Forty-five caliber?
Very close range.
Execution style.
As he was standing against that tree.
Wow.
We found him.
Let's tidy up some for our guest.
All alone?
What? You send your little sidekick
back to LA?
Vultures did a number on him.
Rest of Abuelo's
half-buried in a shallow grave.
You know, he was kind of depressed
when he left here.
Guess he decided to punch his own ticket.
Bury himself before pulling the trigger?
Halfway, you said.
Like most things Abuelo did.
The way I remember,
you two were a couple at one point.
Well, that just means
that I would wake up every morning
and hope that he would die.
Not that I would actually kill him.
Well, reason to think
the person who shot him
might be responsible for
a couple other recent deaths in the park.
Aw, hell!
You called in the cavalry,
did you, Turner?
Just wanted to take a look around.
Make sure none of you in danger.
We are perfectly safe.
You can't just bust in on…
on people's property like this.
These are our personal belongings.
We have constitutional rights!
Glory, you picked the one spot
to pitch a tent
the constitution will not help you.
So, how is Glory's bunch here involved?
It's all connected somehow.
Lucy Cook, the drugs,
Teddy, now Abuelo.
Just need to find something
to convince Glory
to help us fill in the blanks.
Found these. Under a fucking bedpan.
Why would they have a bedpan out here?
Just to dump it in the woods?
Skip the fucking middleman, you know?
This your recycling?
Is that for me or you?
Get through this,
you and I can split one after.
Where'd you get these?
Couldn't say.
Let's say Abuelo gave these to you.
Abuelo was not known
for his altruistic tendencies.
He didn't give me anything.
Oh, except for a lingering case of herpes.
Well, let's say he sold these to you.
Where'd he get them?
I wish I knew. I'd get more.
And you got no interest in helping us
find the people who murdered him?
Good riddance.
Abuelo was an asshole.
And that… that young girl
who went off El Capitan…
Lucy Cook?
Whatever. That's just a name.
She doesn't mean anything to me.
The same as Abuelo.
That's a cold way
to look at things, Glory.
For over two decades,
I worked the same job.
I was very good at it. Better than most.
And then, um,
a week after my 50th birthday,
I was not so gently kicked out the door.
They even misspelled my name
on the termination letter.
And then, a short time later,
the doctor tells me I've got cancer,
but no insurance to do anything about it.
So I figured, fuck it.
If I'm gonna die,
let's do it far away from the real world
as I can get.
Where there's no more fake sympathy
from nurses or doctors
or the insurance voices
saying how sorry they are
while they look at their watches,
hurrying on to the next sad story
with a social security number.
That… was nine years ago.
And I'm still kicking.
Barely, sometimes.
Days where…
I hurt enough
or I am scared enough
that I will try just about anything.
Except fake sympathy…
for girls that I don't know
or men that I don't like.
So forgive me, Agent Turner,
if my tone lacks
a certain degree of warmth.
That's what honesty sounds like.
What you sound like.
Let her go.
Well, that was shocking,
especially as she's always been
so happy to cooperate with us in the past.
We'll keep the rest overnight,
see if any want to give us something
to help them get back out into the wild.
Let me do some background checks,
see if we can find something to leverage.
Speaking of background…
Here's Lucy Cook's DNA results
that you asked for.
They came to me for some reason.
Any interesting threads?
Just one.
No Rory Cook?
He would have been in the system.
He should be in there.
Unless he wasn't the father.
Any talk of that back then?
There's no way that he would have
taken Lucy in after Maggie died,
if he'd known he wasn't her dad.
Hmm.
Let's see where
some of these names lead us.
Anyway, I'm not sure
that it matters now that, uh,
everything seems to be
leaning in a drug-deal direction.
Maybe not for her death, but it could
for what happened back then.
-Agent Turner!
-Yeah?
There's some kid waiting for you.
-What's he want?
-Something about Lucy Cook.
Can I help you?
-Oh, Agent Turner?
-Yeah.
Yeah, I'm Matt Sturge. Nice to meet you.
I was told to wait for you.
Uh, happy birthday.
The other ranger,
he told me it was your birthday.
What do you need?
It's about Grace McRay.
I'm sorry, Lucy Cook.
She was Grace when I knew her.
I don't follow you.
So I grew up over in Yelton.
It's a little anthill of a town
across the line in Nevada.
I saw in the news about her.
I'm pretty sure she lived
down the street from me.
-Lucy Cook?
-Yeah.
With a pastor's family.
See, I went to their church, so…
Uh, she looked a little different.
Hair and stuff, but…
I'd put money on that being her, for sure.
And that's me, right there next to her.
Hmm. With a little imagination, maybe.
-When was the last time you saw her?
-I don't know. Maybe ten years or so.
Pastor Gibbs and his wife said back then
that she left to go live
with her real family.
They say where this real family was?
No. Just sort of got forgotten about.
Like Grace there.
You mind if I hold on to that?
Uh, yeah. Sure. Yeah.
Um…
And also, there's… articles,
online, about a reward
that was being passed out
for information about
her disappearance. $10,000.
Here we go.
Not really missing anymore.
Yeah, well, I thought since
nobody collected before,
there still might be some left over.
This man here will take care
of all your reward details.
Okay. Thank you, sir. Thank you.
Okay.
Please don't run.
I really don't want to have to
chase you down on this thing.
Yeah, Lucy used to go in that mine a lot.
What would she do in there?
Forget who she was.
Become someone else.
Someone without all her pain.
You met here in the park?
Yeah, when we were, like, 16.
Not long after I got here.
And Lucy was already here?
Yeah, yeah. She had a…
a tent somewhere out
in the middle of nowhere,
where no one could find her.
You did.
Well, no, she found me.
It was nice back then.
Felt like we had
the whole world to ourselves.
How long had she been out here?
I think she grew up around the park
until her mom died,
and then… she ran away
from some other place after that.
We had a spot up on Garrison Ridge,
and we were there for a few years.
And then, um…
Lucy got a crush on some guy,
and started being… gone a lot.
Sometimes for days.
What was the guy's name?
Terces.
That's what she called him. It's…
It's "secret" spelled backwards.
Lucy had all kinds of secrets,
but… that one was her favorite.
I mean, God knows why. He's…
He's not a nice guy.
He got her into all sorts of bad shit.
And after that, when I'd see her,
she'd either be carrying drugs or cash,
just depending on
which direction she was going.
Did you ever go with her?
See who she was working for?
Where they were?
No, ma'am.
That shit scared me.
I remember she'd come back
all, like, beat up sometimes.
And, uh, one day she left,
and she never came back.
Did you see Lucy again after that?
Maybe in the distance sometimes
when she was dealing with Abuelo.
Uh, they had a spot in this gulch
where she would go drop drugs,
and he'd swap it out for cash and…
I saw her near there,
like, maybe a week or so ago,
and she was carrying the bag
that she uses for deliveries.
She was alone?
Yeah.
What about someone else
who worked with Abuelo?
He was with Pakuna a lot.
Pakuna?
Yeah.
-He lived with you guys?
-He was friends with Abuelo.
They'd go do their walkabouts together.
I should clear out too.
You need somewhere to stay?
I got places, ma'am.
Can you tell me where that gulch is?
Where Lucy and Abuelo would make the swap?
Had it buried out there, but it was empty.
And the girl?
She saw Lucy Cook make the drop?
Yeah.
If that buzzard dude's math is right,
Abuelo was already dead.
So someone else knew it was there.
Could be this other squatter
she told me about. Pakuna.
Said he was the closest
of their bunch with Abuelo.
He's refused to talk so far,
but we're still
holding him at the station.
He might know who Lucy and Abuelo
were moving product for.
Well, whoever they are,
their operation would have to be
on the east side of the mine.
Maybe we take a chopper tomorrow.
Take a look around.
-If we get lucky, we might spot something.
-Hmm.
Where'd all this stuff come from?
It's from the house Lucy Cook grew up in.
She always looked so happy.
Man, life can change in a blink.
I'm gonna go pick up my kid.
See you tomorrow.
In a blink.
Jim Beam.
Celebrating your special occasions
in public now, huh?
I admire that.
We are who we are.
What do you know about Abuelo?
Just that he's dead.
I need to find myself a new witch doctor.
Quick.
Any thoughts on who killed him?
Abuelo dealt so much shit,
the list of possibles is long.
What was your cut?
I'm not sure I follow.
You're wildlife management, right?
Yeah, not that wild.
Maybe the occasional discount
for looking the other way, but…
What about his supplier?
The one with the X?
What was your deal with them?
Beyond the point of entry, Kyle,
that is outside of my jurisdiction.
You've never been one
to turn away free money.
Maybe if I know who to send a bill to,
I would've, but…
like I said, I'm just a loyal customer.
Hey, speaking of interesting info,
that, uh, that Jane Doe of yours
who took a header off El Capitan,
she's a real miracle child, huh?
Comes roaring back to life
like Jesus Christ himself.
Just took 15 years instead of three days.
Maybe you'll do better on the case
this time around.
French fries are my favorite.
Me too. Don't tell anyone, though.
Mommy's gonna make us a spinach smoothie,
cover our tracks.
Come on. Whoop.
Okay, come on. Oop. Bah-bah-bah.
Wash your hands and you can help me.
Mommy, look.
It lights up.
Where did you get that?
Gael!
Hey, Mommy.
Gael, come over here to me.
You shouldn't be here.
I'm just checking out the area.
You didn't tell me you were heading here.
I'm pretty sure
my lip was too swollen to talk.
That shit again?
Well, you give as good as you take, Naya.
It's time for bed, Gael.
Hey. I'll put him in.
He needs a bath first.
-Tell your father bye. He needs to leave.
-Where am I going?
Up to you, but not staying here.
Well, as you know, I'm not exactly
bringing in a regular paycheck right now.
-So unless you pay for my hotel--
-You need to go back to LA.
Hey, that sounds great.
You two come with me.
And while you're there,
you can tell those IA fucks
I had nothing to do
with that asshole's money.
I'm not lying for you.
I need my badge back, Naya.
Otherwise, what am I supposed to do?
Not my problem.
Maybe.
Maybe not.
Hey, come here, G-man.
You like that?
That's a cool one, huh, G-man?
Get your hand off him.
Only three of us were in
that cooker's apartment, Naya.
Me, you, and Rowell.
You back my story… it's two to one.
They got no proof of anything,
and I'm back on my job.
You got it?
Gael, go turn on the tub.
Give me the car. I'll be right there.
You can play with it after.
I stay here tonight.
We all go down tomorrow,
and then this is all over.
Fine.
Then we never see you again.
If you come near either of us tonight,
I'll shoot you in the fucking head.
I swear to God.
Naya…
I mean,
not exactly the warm reunion
I was hoping for.
Mommy!
Coming.
Not too hot.
Ayo, G-man.
Hey, remember we used to play
that bath ball game with--
Gael!
It's okay, baby. Stay down.
Hey, that bullet come back?
I shoot whoever you thought I did?
I'm not sure yet.
Tell me who got shot,
I'll tell you if it's mine, but…
you know me, Kyle.
Not in the habit of shooting people
unless I'm getting paid for it.
Back in Kabul, we used to throw
100 bucks in a pot,
me and the snipers, for which of us--
Did you know her?
The girl.
Lucy Cook.
Kyle,
you and me talking like this
about dead bodies,
it's almost like
we're working together again.
We've never worked together.
Tomato, tomahto.
If you're in this somehow,
I'm gonna find out.
Then what, Kyle?
No, I'm curious.
Exactly what the fuck
would you do about it?
Hey, uh…
Esther Avalos.
Got a hell of a cute smile.
But boy, does she ask a lot of questions.
Mainly about you, by the way.
Wonder what you must have done
to pique her interest so.
I told her it'd been a few years,
I'd have to think about it,
see what I could remember.
What do you think I should remember
about that Sanderson fellow, Kyle?
When was the first time I saw him, or…
maybe when was the last time?
I just love this song.
Who is this exactly?
Ah, never mind. You two are too young
to appreciate the finer things.
Kyle, can I borrow you for a moment?
Just in time.
-Good to see you, Shane.
-You too, Paul.
Say hi to Jill, Kyle.
Keep going, buddy.
What, you're coming home with me now?
Well, if I was, I'd sure as hell
be holding those keys and not you.
Why am I missing a spark plug? Really?
I'm sure it'll turn up
when you're ready to go.
Oh, I'm ready to go now.
How do you think this ends?
Find out what happened to her.
I'm not talking about Lucy Cook.
I'm talking about you, this right here.
I don't know, Paul.
What do you want me to say?
It wasn't your fault.
Not Caleb, not Lucy,
not the kid from the bait store.
None of it!
So at some point,
you have to stop torturing yourself.
You have to.
And if that means taking a break
from this place, then so be it.
I'm not leaving here.
I'm not leaving him.
That part of Caleb that you hang on to,
that'll be with you wherever you go,
whether it's Glacier or Acadia.
But you have to stop
beating yourself to death with memories.
Yeah.
Maybe after.
But I owe this girl.
Do something right by her.
Thanks.
Wasn't sure if you're in the mood
for steak or chicken,
but, you know, back in the day
when I was doing it too hard,
there's nothing like banana cream pie
to clear the fog.
You want to tell me
what that was with Maguire?
No.
Okay.
There's a restraining order,
so he's not supposed to come near us.
I thought moving up here might be better.
He's naturally lazy, so I figured
the drive wouldn't be worth it to him.
I thought you said
he had no real interest in you two.
He doesn't.
Not for him.
It's just a power move.
Letting me know he'll do what he wants
unless I help clear him.
You still thirsty? Can I get him a drink?
Yeah. Bourbon's behind the coffee.
Ha-ha-ha.
You're so close.
How old are you?
Four?
You like being four?
Enjoy it. It gets harder.
-You have a lot of boxes.
-I like boxes.
No, no. Not that box.
All right. Gael, here. Have some water.
All right. We gotta go to bed now.
It's okay we steal your couch?
I'll get something figured out
for tomorrow.
-You sure you don't mind?
-Are you kidding me? I love this.
I told Kyle I wasn't gonna go in today so…
Thank you so much.
I'll grab him as soon as we get back.
No rush. We'll just be here.
All right, playing,
maybe we'll go take a walk
and see what we find.
Raccoons?
Do you like raccoons?
Okay, then no. No raccoons.
Okay, you be good for Miss Jill, okay?
Uh-hee-hee.
Let me grab my stuff.
Nice of you to do this.
Oh, please. Thanks… for asking me.
Bye, Gael!
Anything?
Just more trees. Lots of them.
That greenblood the girl told you
was close to Abuelo…
Pakuna.
I want you to reach out to Milch.
Have him pull him out.
-You wanna ask him some questions?
-No.
I want him to take him back
to the meadow and cut him loose.
No supplies. No food.
No water. No nothing.
Copy.
Which one of you is Gary Horowitz?
It's Pakuna.
Means "deer jumping downhill."
Yeah? Good for you.
Bruce Milch. Means "I don't give a shit."
Let's go.
There's nothing here.
Just as God intended.
What am I supposed to do now?
I don't know, Pakuna.
Go get a fucking job.
Sunshine beating on the good times
Moonlight raising from the grave
String band playing
Worn-out honky-tonks
Pretty young thing
Going dancing in the rain
High-heel lady
Spitting at the Nickajacks
Businessman with a needle and a spoon
Coyote chewing on a cigarette
Pack o' young boys
Going howlin' at the moon
Hey darlin'
Sleeping on the blacktop
Running through the trees, honey
Hey darlin'
Leaving for the next town
Less'n my sense catches up with me
Three dead in a crash on the number 4
Two witnesses below and up high
Not sure whose will be done
You can call me a sinner
For a-wondering why
Hey darlin'
Sleeping on the blacktop
Running through the trees, honey
Hey darlin'
Leaving for the next town
Less'n my sense catches up with me
It's me.
Pakuna.
Rangers came. Took everything.
Then they found Abuelo.
How?
I don't know.
But they asked a lot of questions.
-What did you tell them?
-Nothing.
I swear.
I told you. I'm not like Abuelo.
I won't ever skim or screw you guys over.
At least not as long
as you get what you want, right?
I won't screw you over.
You said that.
Let's hope that you're right.
Let's have a chat, Pakuna.